Guide to the Luther Bradish Papers 1801-1863, 1963 MS 71
New-York Historical Society
Luther Bradish papers
1801-1863, 1963
New-York Historical Society
Bradish, Luther, 1783-1863
MS 71
6.875 Linear feet in eighteen document boxes and two oversize folders.
This collection consists of a large variety of papers relating to Luther Bradish (1783-1863), a former President of the New-York Historical Society. Bradish led a notable life serving as an attorney, a representative in the New York State Assembly, Speaker of the Assembly, and Lieutenant Governor of New York. He was a supporter of many New York based organizations, educational institutions, and cultural institutions. Bradish also championed technological modernization. The documents found in this collection consist of personal correspondence, drafts of Bradish's correspondences/speeches, political/legal documents, financial statements, invitations, sketches, maps, circulars, and newspaper clippings.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Luther Bradish was a prominent 19th century American lawyer and politician. Bradish was born on September 15, 1783 in Cummington, Massachusetts. Bradish graduated from Williams College in 1804. He studied law, passed the bar, and became an attorney. During the War of 1812, Bradish served in the U.S. Army. In 1814, he married Elizabeth Gibbs, daughter of the mineralogist George Gibbs, however, the marriage was short lived as Elizabeth gave birth to a stillborn child and died in childbirth in 1816. Bradish married Mary Eliza Hart in 1839 and they had a daughter together.
In 1819, President James Monroe and Secretary of State John Quincy Adams recruited Bradish to negotiate a commerce and shipping treaty with the Ottoman Empire, however, this treaty with the Ottomans was not ratified until May 1830 under the presidency of Andrew Jackson. In addition to visiting the Ottomans in Turkey, Bradish also spent time exploring the European continent.
After returning from Europe, Luther Bradish moved to Moira, NY in 1826. He purchased several tracts of land and became a major proprietor in the town. While residing in Moira, Bradish was elected to the New York State Assembly as a representative for Franklin County. He served in the Assembly from 1827 to 1830 and again from 1836 to 1838. During his second term, he was elected as Speaker of the House.
Bradish was a member of the Whig Party and between 1839 and 1842, he spent two terms as Lieutenant Governor of New York, working with his Whig colleague, Governor William H. Seward. Bradish was a supporter of the abolition of slavery and during his campaign for the Lieutenant Governor position, he received support from the abolitionist community. In 1842 he ran for Governor, but was defeated by Democrat, William C. Bouck. Under the Presidency of Millard Fillmore in 1855, Bradish briefly served as Assistant United States Treasurer.
During his lifetime, Luther Bradish was affiliated with several organizations and institutions. He was on the Board of Trustees of the Franklin Academy and the University of the City of New York. He was also President of the New-York Historical Society from 1850 until his death and the American Bible Society from 1862 until his death.
Bradish was also a supporter of science, technology, and modernization. He was actively involved in building new roads within New York State, as well as canals and railroads. He was a member of the American Agricultural Society and the American Geographical and Statistical Society. In 1859, Bradish pushed for the establishment of an astronomical observatory in Central Park.
Luther Bradish died of typhoid dysentery on August 30, 1863 in Newport, Rhode Island. His body was returned to New York and he is buried at Green-Wood Cemetery in Brooklyn.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically and placed into fifteen document size boxes, as well as three half-document size boxes. Some items have been placed in two oversize folders. Although the majority of the collection is chronological, the latter part of the collection consists of undated material.
It should be noted that some documents had been previously processed, removed, and placed into separate boxes. These documents were re-integrated chronologically into the overall collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of eighteen document boxes and two oversize folders, all containing papers relating to Luther Bradish, a former President of the New-York Historical Society. Luther Bradish was a prominent 19th century American lawyer and politician, as well as an avid supporter of charitable organizations and technological advancements in New York State. The documents found in this collection are arranged chronologically and consist of personal correspondence, drafts of Bradish's correspondences/speeches, political/legal documents, financial statements, invitations, sketches, maps, circulars, and newspaper clippings.
The Luther Bradish Papers is rich with correspondence from prominent 19th century figures including Francis Granger, Gerrit Smith, John Quincy Adams, Daniel D. Barnard, Elkanah Watson, Frederic de Peyster, William Henry Harrison, George Gibbs, William Bouck, Henry Clay, Nathaniel P. Tallmadge, Thurlow Weed, Henry Bell Van Rensselaer, Millard Fillmore, Martin Van Buren, and others. The collection also contains drafts of Bradish's outgoing correspondence.
During his time as a young attorney, Luther Bradish acted as executor for the estate of Ichabod Brush of Demerara, British Guiana, and Huntington, Long Island. Many of the letters and papers for 1801-1815 pertain to the settlement of Brush's estate. Documents relate to Brush's plantation "Vigilance" in Demerara, as well as legal documents and correspondence involving John Brush, Ebenezer Brush, and other members of the Brush family.
The Luther Bradish Papers contains documents relating to Bradish's travels abroad, specifically when he was in Turkey negotiating a trade alliance with the Ottoman Empire (1821-1826). There is some correspondence between Bradish and the Reis Effendi of the Sublime Porte (Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Ottoman Empire), draft correspondence where Bradish describes his travels, as well as documents written in foreign languages. There are also some hand drawn sketches of European landmarks such as Elba Island.
Relating to Bradish's political career, the collection contains several petitions, political circulars, discussion of contemporary politics (Whigs, Locofocos, American party, reform to certain laws) as well as copies of Acts passed by the New York State Assembly and New York State Senate. There are also letters of support for political candidates and correspondence between members of the New York State legislature. The collection also contains documents relating to Luther Bradish's election as Lieutenant Governor of New York and his failed campaign for the position of Governor of New York.
The collection consists of numerous documents relating to the construction of canals, railroads, and roads throughout New York State. Papers relating to the creation of the Port Kent-Hopkinton road, Chenango Canal, Delaware-Hudson Canal Company, Great Northern Railroad, Hudson-Berkshire Railroad Company, Ogdenburgh-Lake Champlain Railroad, Erie Canal, Canal Commission, New York-Erie Railroad Company, and more can be found within this collection.
With regards to Bradish's connection to Moira, N.Y., the collection contains numerous receipts, mortgages, land deeds, survey maps, local political documents, and correspondence. Robert Watts and Peter Kean, Bradish's business partners in Moira, are prominent figures within these documents.
Papers relating to the numerous organizations and institutions Luther Bradish was a part of can also be found within the collection. These include documents relating to the: New-York Historical Society, American Bible Society, University of the City of New York, American Agricultural Society, Protestant Episcopal Society for the Promotion of Evangelical Knowledge, DeWitt Clinton Memorial Association, American Geographical and Statistical Society, New York College of Physicians and Surgeons, and the American Institute.
The collection also contains various legal documents such as several Last Wills and Testaments, powers of attorney, estate inventories, indentures, and contracts.
Miscellaneous documents relating to the abolition of slavery, the prolonged development of an astronomical observatory in Central Park, various invitations, family matters, the Episcopal Church, Trinity Church, the Free Academy, Greek independence from Ottoman rule, and more can also be found within this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
152 invitations acquired as a gift from George A. Zabriskie on Oct 20, 1939 and August 7, 1941.
The provenance for the entire Luther Bradish Papers is not definitively known, however, it is highly probable the collection was acquired before 1984, based on pre-existing notes in card catalogue. It is also likely that some documents were added to the collection over time.
Related Materials
New-York Historical Society holds other documents concerning Luther Bradish in other collections and in standalone documents in the American Historical Manuscripts Collection (AHMC). Search Bobcat for "Bradish" to identify these other materials.
Central Park (New York, N.Y.); Decedents' estates; Real property -- New York (State); Demerara; Huntington (N.Y.: Town); Moira (N.Y.); Turkey -- Foreign relations -- Treaties.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; New York (State) -- History -- 19th century.; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Letters (correspondence); Minutes (administrative records); Legal documents.; Bills (legislative records); Official documents; Maps.; Circulars (fliers).; Accounts.; Canals -- New York (State); Railroads -- New York (State) -- New York.; Roads -- New York (State) -- New York.; Abolitionists -- New York (State) -- New York -- Societies, etc.; Philanthropy.; Sketches.; Banks and banking -- New York (State) -- New York.; Insurance; Agriculture -- New York (State).; Invitations.; Petitions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Astronomy; Gibraltar -- Description and travel.; Saint Lawrence County (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Appleton, Thomas, 1763-1840; Bainbridge, William, 1774-1833; Beck, Theodric Romeyn, 1791-1855; Beekman, James W. (James William), 1815-1877; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1795-1858; Carroll, Charles H. (Charles Holker), 1794-1865; Channing, William Ellery, 1780-1842; Gibbs, George, 1776-1833; Gibbs, William C. (William Channing), 1789-1871; Granger, Francis, 1792-1868; Ketchum, Hiram; Minturn, Robert Bowne, 1805-1866; Spencer, Ambrose, 1765-1848; Wendell, John L. (John Lansing), 1785-1861; Watson, Elkanah, 1758-1842; Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848; Van Schaick, Myndert, 1782-1865; De Peyster, Frederic, 1796-1882; Harrison, William Henry, 1773-1841; Mann, Abijah, 1793-1868; Kemble, Gouverneur, 1786-1875; Bouck, William C., 1786-1859; Rochester, William Beatty, 1789-1838; Weed, Thurlow, 1797-1882; Tallmadge, Nathaniel Pitcher, 1795-1864; Smith, Gerrit, 1797-1874; Van Rensselaer, Henry, 1811-1864; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852.; Barnard, Daniel D. (Daniel Dewey), 1797-1861; Ruggles, Samuel B. (Samuel Bulkley), 1800-1881; Van Rensselaer, Stephen, 1764-1839; Perry, Matthew Calbraith, 1794-1858; Fillmore, Millard, 1800-1874; Van Buren, Martin, 1782-1862; Hone, Philip, 1780-1851; Delavan, Edward C. (Edward Cornelius), 1793-1871; Holgate, Jerome B. (Jerome Bonaparte); Hudson, David, 1782-1860; Duer, William, 1805-1879; Dickinson, Daniel S. (Daniel Stevens), 1800-1866; Folsom, George, 1802-1869; Noyes, William Curtis, 1805-1864; Frelinghuysen, Theodore, 1787-1862; Butler, Charles, 1802-1897; Renwick, James, 1818-1895; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Gibbs, Wolcott, 1822-1908; Bryant, William Cullen, 1794-1878; Astor, William B. (William Backhouse), 1792-1875; Reed, William B. (William Bradford), 1806-1876; Boardman, Henry A. (Henry Augustus), 1808-1880; Haswell, Chas. H. (Charles Haynes), 1809-1907; Aspinwall, William Henry, 1807-1875; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Field, Maunsell B. (Maunsell Bradhurst), 1822-1875; Fish, Hamilton, 1808-1893; King, Preston, 1806-1865; Brush, Ichabod, -1809; Wilkins, Martin S.; Gibbs, Helen Elizabeth; Randolph, D. M.; Chasseaud, J.; Allen, Frederick P., 1798-1878; Barclay, Henry; Chambers, Corry, active approximately 1856; Columbus (Ship of the line); New-York Historical Society; American Geographical and Statistical Society; Agricultural Society of the United States; American Institute of the City of New York; University of the City of New York; American Bible Society; Trinity Church (New York, N.Y.); Whig Party (New York, N.Y.)
- Correspondence, Legal documents, 1801-1805 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Legal documents, 1806 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  In addition to general correspondence, this folder contains documents relating to: the Brush family, Ichabod Brush's estate, and papers relating to his plantation in Demerara.
- Correspondence, 1807-1808 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Legal Documents, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  In addition to general correspondence, this folder contains documents relating to the Brush Estate (plantation in Demerara).
- Correspondence (Folder 1 of 2), 1810 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This folder contains general correspondence. See Folder 2 for oversize material.
- Correspondence, Oversized (Folder 2 of 2), 1810 (Folder OS-Medium)
  This oversize folder contains the Last Will and Testament of French Kellam and a slave roster entitled "Monthly List of Plantation Vigilance-December 1810." These documents were removed from the origial 1810 folder.
- Correspondence, Certificates (Folder 1 of 2), 1811 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  In addition to general correspondence, this folder contains documents certifying Luther Bradish as a practicing attorney in the state of New York. See second folder for oversized documents.
- Correspondence, Certificates, Oversized (Folder 2 of 2), 1811 (Folder OS-Medium)
  Slave rosters entitled "Monthly List of Plantation Vigilance-January 1811" and "Monthly List of Plantation Vigilance-February 1811" were removed from 1811 folder and placed in oversized folder
- Correspondence, Certificates, Legal documents, 1812-1814 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  In addition to general correspondence, this folder contains indentures and documents certifying Luther Bradish as a practicing attorney in the state of New York.
- Correspondence, Legal documents, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- The Stocking Society, 1814-1815 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  The Stocking Society was formed in October 1814 - during the War of 1812 - with the purpose of "procuring socks, mockasins, mittens, and cloth goods for the soldiers of the United States and the Militia of the State of New York now employed in defence of their country." (quoted from collection)
  Folder contains Stocking Society circulars, correspondence, and ledgers.
- Correspondence, Legal documents (Folder 1 of 2), 1816 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Some materials in this folder pertain to Moira, N.Y. See Folder 2 for oversized content.
- Correspondence, Legal documents, Oversized (Folder 2 of 2), 1816 (Folder OS-Medium)
  Deed between William/Eliza Cooper to Frederick DePeyster and Luther Bradish removed from 1816 folder and placed in oversized folder. Deed between William/Eliza Cooper to Luther Bradish also removed from 1816 folder and placed in oversized folder.
- Correspondence, Legal documents (Folder 1 of 2), 1817 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  This folder largely consists of correspondence and legal documents. There are also two slave registrar lists, legal/financial documents related to Moira, and some Italian documents.
- Correspondence, Legal documents, Oversized (Folder 2 of 2), 1817 (Folder OS-Medium)
  Indenture between Frederick/Ann DePeyster and Luther Bradish removed from 1817 folder and placed into an oversized folder.
- Correspondence, Financial documents, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  In addition to general correspondence, this folder contains letters and legal documents between Bradish and George Gibbs. These papers relate to the death of Bradish's wife, Helen Elizabeth Gibbs.
- Correspondence, Legal documents, 1819 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1820 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Among other documents, this folder includes papers relating to Bradish's negotiations with the Reis Effendi of the Sublime Porte (Minister of Foreign Affairs for the Ottoman Empire).
  This folder also a letter written by Bradish whilst traveling on the U.S.S. Columbus detailing his trip to Gibraltar, as well as a 36 page letter written by Bradish from Turkey describing his experiences in Constantinople and attempts to negotiate with the Ottomans.
  Folder also contains receipts relating to Moira.
- Correspondence, 1821 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Folder includes, among other documents, papers relating to Bradish's negotiations with the Reis Effendi of the Sublime Porte (Minister of Foreign Affairs for the Ottoman Empire). Some of the content of this folder is written in French.
- Correspondence, 1822 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  The content of this folder mainly focuses on Bradish's travels in Europe. Some of the correspondence is written in French and Italian. There are also some receipts relating to Moira.
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents, 1823-1824 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  In addition to correspondence, a significant portion of this folder contains receipts relating to Moira. There are also a few documents written in French and Russian.
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents, 1825 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Among other documents, this folder includes papers relating to Bradish's overseas finances with Baring Brothers and Moira.
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents, 1826 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  In addition to general correspondence, this folder includes papers relating to Bradish's overseas finances with Baring Brothers and Moira related business.
  The folder also contains a draft letter from Luther Bradish to John Quincy Adams discussing negotiations with the Sublime Porte.
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents (6 Folders), 1827 (Box 3, Folder 2-7)
  1827 is divided into six folders covering a variety of topics including: the Greek Committee and Greek independence from Ottoman rule (Folders 2, 3), Moira, Luther Bradish's personal business, letters relating to J. Fenimore Cooper (Folder 8), as well as documents relating to the estate of George Gibbs and correspondence with Governor William Gibbs (Folders 1, 3, 4, 6, 7).
  These folders also contain documents discussing the creation of a road between Lake Champlain and Hopkinton (Folder 2, 8) and railroad development in New York State (specifically 7, 8).
- Correspondence, Legal documents (3 of 6 Folders), 1828 January - 1828 March (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  January-March 1828 is divided into three folders covering a variety of subjects including: the estate of George Gibbs, railroads, Luther Bradish's personal business, the creation of a road between Lake Champlain and Hopkinton (Folder 10), as well as Moira.
  These folders also contain correspondence from Elkanah Watson (Folder 7).
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents (3 of 6 Folders), 1828 April - 1828 December (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  April-December 1828 is divided into three folders covering a variety of subjects including: the estate of George Gibbs (Folder 1), Luther Bradish's personal business, the creation of a road between Port Kent and Hopkinton (Folder 1), as well as Moira.
  These folders also contain a draft letter from Luther Bradish to John Quincy Adams (Folder 1) and a circular from the Central Corresponding Committee discussing the upcoming 1828 presidential election and the candidates - Andrew Jackson, Martin Van Buren, and John Quincy Adams (Folder 3).
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents (9 Folders), 1829 (Box 4, Folder 4-12)
  1829 is divided into nine folders covering a variety of subjects including: the Delaware-Hudson Canal Company (Folders 5, 6), reform to Auction Laws (Folders 5, 6, 8, 10), reform to Banking Laws and opening of banks (Folders 6, 8, 9), Moira, as well as the creation of a road between Port Kent and Hopkinton (Folders 5, 6, 8, 10).
  These folders also contain correspondence with Myndert Van Schaick (Folders 5, 6, 10) Frederic de Peyster (Folder 5), William Henry Harrison (Folder 10), and George Gibbs (Folder 11).
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents (6 Folders), 1830 (Box 5, Folder 1-6)
  1830 is divided into six folders covering a variety of subjects including: Moira, Bank Bills (Folders 1, 5), canals (Folders 1, 2, 3), creation of roads (Folders 1, 2, 5), creation of railroads (Folders 5, 6), Luther Bradish's personal business, Bradish's property on Pearl St in New York City (Folders 1, 2, 5), the Clinton Hall Project (Folder 2), and Common Schools (Folders 1, 3, 5).
  These folders also contain correspondence with William Henry Harrison (Folders 1, 3, 5). In his letters, Harrison asks Bradish about the costs associated with building a road in Chateaugay, NY and discusses bills allowing a town tax in Potsdam, Massena, and Canton for bridge building.
- Correspondence, Legal, Financial documents (2 Folders), 1831 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  1831 is divided into two folders covering several subjects including: the Franklin Academy, discussion of contemporary politics, and Moira.
  There is also correspondence with Abijah Mann Jr. and General Henri La Fayette Villaume Ducoudray Holstein (Folder 7).
  The correspondence between Luther Bradish and Abijah Mann Jr. largely revolves around a dispute regarding an article Mann published in the Franklin Republican on February 21, 1831. The article was disparaging towards Bradish and Bradish demanded Mann apologize.
- Correspondence, Legal documents (2 Folders), 1832 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  1832 is divded into two folders covering a variety of topics including: Moira, the New York Harlem Rail Road Company (Folder 9), the 1832 National Republican Convention (Folder 10), as well as business relating to William Charming and George Gibbs (Folder 10).
  There is also correspondence from Abijah Mann Jr. (Folder 9) continuing his argument with Bradish over an article published in the Franklin Republic in 1831 and Francis Granger (Folder 10) discussing the National Republican Convention.
- Correspondence, Legal documents, 1833 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  This folder contains various material, some of which relates to the 1832 Democratic National Convention and Moira.
- Correspondence, 1834 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  The contents of this folder mainly focus on Moira and contemporary politics.
- Correspondence (2 Folders), 1835 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
  1835 is divided into two folders covering a variety of topics including: Moira, discussion of political/Whig state conventions (Folder 14), mention of the Brush River Canal (Folder 14), and controversy surrounding the creation of the town of Fonda (Folder 14).
  These folders also include correspondence from Elkanah Watson (Folder 13).
- Correspondence (1 of 3 Folders), 1836 January-1836 March (Box 5, Folder 15)
  The January-March 1836 folder contains documents relating to: Merchant's Fire Insurance Company, United States Fire Insurance Company of the City of New York, the New York and Erie Railroad, several circulars outlining acts passed by the New York State Assembly and Senate, as well as discussion of William Henry Harrison as President and Francis Granger as Vice President.
- Correspondence, Legal, Political documents (2 of 3 Folders), 1836 April-1836 December (Box 6, Folder 1-2)